<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
    There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
    An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC6830 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6830.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6763 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6763.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4632 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4632.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
    please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
    (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-rpp-00" ipr="trust200902">
 <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
   <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->

   <title abbrev="rpp">The Routing Preference Protocol</title>

   <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

   <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

   <author fullname="François Devienne" initials="F." surname="Devienne">
     <organization>BORDER 6</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street> TO BE FILLED</street>

         <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

         <city></city>

         <region></region>

         <code></code>

         <country>France</country>
       </postal>

       <phone></phone>

       <email>francois.devienne@border6.com</email>

       <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Mateusz Viste" initials="M." surname="Viste">
     <organization>BORDER 6</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street> TO BE FILLED</street>

         <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

         <city></city>

         <region></region>

         <code></code>

         <country>France</country>
       </postal>

       <phone></phone>

       <email>mateusz.viste@border6.com</email>

       <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
   </author>

	<author fullname="Wenqin Shao" initials="W.Q." surname="Shao">
     <organization>Telecom ParisTech</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>23, avenue d'Italie</street>

         <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

         <city>Paris</city>

         <region></region>

         <code>75013</code>

         <country>France</country>
       </postal>

       <phone></phone>

       <email>wenqin.shao@telecom-paristech.fr</email>

       <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
   </author>

   <date month="July" year="2016" />

   <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill
        in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to
	 specify just the year. -->

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>General</area>

   <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

   <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>inter-domain routing</keyword>
   <keyword>traffic engineering</keyword>
   <keyword>inbound</keyword>

   <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
     <t>This memo describes a protocol allowing an Autonomous System (AS) to
       perform inbound traffic engineering by
       communicating directly its inbound routing preferences
       to the networks that send out the traffic.</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>Routing Preference Protocol (RPP) is an application layer protocol.
     It aims at providing a routing-protocol-independant interface
     for Autonomous Systems (ASes) to communicate their inbound routing preferences,
     on the granularity of per BGP prefixes it originates,
     directly to the traffic sourcing prefixes,
     across the internet.</t>

     <section anchor="motiv" title="Motivation">
    	<t>Inbound Traffic Engineering (TE) in inter-domain routing consists in distributing the
    	incoming traffic on to the available paths. 
    	Manipulate inbound traffic with fine granularity allows, for example, congestion avoidance
    	and transit cost minimisation.
     	Current practices, deeply coupled with underlying inter-domain routing mechanism,
     	fall short of such capabilities.</t>

     	<t>With the Border Gateway Protocol (BGP), one can use selective announcement,
     	AS-PATH prepending, MED and BGP community attributes to influence the routing of
     	incoming traffic. The effects of all these appraoches remain coarse, uncertain and
     	hard to manage according to <xref target="BGP_INBOUND_TE">Shao2015</xref>.</t>

	 	<t>Locator/Identifier Separation Protocol (LISP) <xref target="RFC6830">RFC&nbsp;6830</xref>,
	 	an alternative inter-domain routing protocol, allows the available routing options
	 	(RLOC in LISP terminology) for destination prefixes (EID-prefixes) be registered with
	 	configurable weights. Such expression of routing preference (EID-to-RLOC mapping)
	 	is formulated by destination AS and is learnt and executed by the AS sourcing
	 	the traffic.
	 	However, its benefit is bundled with the deployment of LISP,
	 	especially the EID-to-RLOC mapping system.
	 	It requires packets in EID address space be encapsulated in RLOC space when routed,
	 	which implies disruptive forwarding plane changes and eventually hinders the adoption of LISP.</t>
		
   		<t>The intention of RPP is to provide a routing-protocol-independent 
    	channel to targetedly diffuse LISP-like inbound routing preference.
    	With the wide and still increasing deployment of multihoming, we assume that the
    	underlying inter-domain routing protocol, e.g. BGP, provides most of the time sufficient route disjointness,
    	which allows a destination prefix be reached by different ingress providers if the source prefixe
    	changes its egress providers.</t>
    	
	 </section>

   <section anchor="scope" title="Scope">
    <t>This document specifies the following issues:
    <list style="symbols">
        <t>First, how the RPP server of a prefix
         MUST be registered and discovered.</t>
        <t>Second, functionality and formats of protocol messages.</t>
      </list></t>
    <t>The interplay between RPP and the underlying routing system is up to each adopting network,
    and is thus beyond this memo.</t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="about" title="About This Memo">
    <t>The following of the memo is organised as follows.
    <xref target="terms" /> specifies the terms used in the document.
    <xref target="server_addr" /> describes the registration and discovery of RPP servers.
    <xref target="proto" /> details the protocol exchange and message format.
    At the end of the memo, <xref target="IANA">IANA</xref>
    and <xref target="Security">security</xref> considerations are provided.</t>
   </section>

 </section>

   <section anchor="terms" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

      <t>Here below are the definition of terms in this memo:
       <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
       	 <!--change network to AS-->
       	 <t hangText="Destination AS/prefix"> The AS/prefix receiving traffic.</t>
         <t hangText="Source AS/prefix"> The AS/prefix sending out traffic.</t>
         <t hangText="Inbound routing preference"> It is about how destination prefixes prefer to
         receive traffic, e.g. a specific upstream AS is prioritised.</t>
         <t hangText="Message"> The unite of information exchanged through RPP.</t>
         <t hangText="Command">The type of information carried by an RPP message.</t>
         <t hangText="Prefix"> Routable prefix in the size announced by its originating
         Autonomous System.</t>
         <t hangText="RPP server"> Host with a public IPv4 and/or a IPv6 address that speaks RPP
         on behalf of a set of prefixes.</t>
         <t hangText="Delegated prefixes"> A set of prefixes that is under the regime of
         one common RPP server specified by the context.</t>
      </list></t>
   </section>


	 <section anchor="ov" title="Overview">
     <t>RPP described in the memo provides a LISP-like mapping system,
 	 yet independant of LISP and any other inter-domain routing framework.
 	 Only inbound routing preference, homologue to EID-to-RLOC mapping in LISP,
 	 is exchanged through RPP.
 	 ASes that adopt RPP can freely choose their preferred way of executing learnt
     routing preference.</t>

     <t>Different from LISP, RPP does not follow a request-reply mechanism.
     With RPP, the destination AS pushes its inbound routing preferences
     unidirectionally to the source AS.
     The source AS SHOULD satisfy the communicated
     preferences, as long as the later doesn't violate its local routing policies.
     </t>

     <t> One and only one server sending out and receving routing preference is REQUIRED
     for each prefix that wishes to enable this protocol.
     Each RPP server is identified by its public IP address.
     It MUST have one and only one IPv4 address, and MAY as well have one and only one IPv6 address.
     Multiple prefixes, for example thoes belonging to a same AS, MAY mutualize one server.
     </t>
     
     <t>Another major difference from LISP is that
     RPP does not require a dedicated mapping system.
     The protocol messages are directly exchanged between the RPP servers of the
	 source and destination prefixes.
	 DNS system is leveraged to discover the RPP server of a prefix.
	 </t>
	 </section>

   	<section anchor="server_addr" title="Discover RPP server">
   	<t>In order for the RPP server of a prefix to be discovered, a specific DNS record is REQUIRED. 
   	The record MUST be of TXT type defined in <xref target="RFC1035">RFC&nbsp;1035</xref>.
   	Meanwhile, the domain name of the entry MUST be the IN-ADDR.ARPA/IP6.ARPA domain, as well defined in
   	<xref target="RFC1035">RFC&nbsp;1035</xref>, for the network address of
   	the destination prefix.
   	The destination prefix is implicitly assumed to be of the same size 
   	as announced by the underlying routing protocol, i.e. BGP currently.
   	For exemple, the network that owns the prefixe 185.86.53.0/24, SHALL install the following
   	record on its DNS server, assuming 185.86.53.1 is the public IPv4 address of the RPP server:
   	<list style="empty">
   	<t>0.53.86.185.in-addr.arpa. IN TXT "RDE:185.86.53.1"</t>
   	</list>
   	"RDE" in the response stands for "RPP Decision Engine".
   	Following "RDE:" in the response string, SHOULD be the public IPv4 or IPv6
   	address of the RPP server.</t>

    <t>In case that the RPP server discovery is failed, e.g. target prefix
    is not RPP-enabled, only the routing preference communication becomes impossible.
    Normal routing behaviour is not at all impacted.</t>

   	</section>

   	<section anchor="proto" title="The protocol">
   		<t>RPP is a client-server protocol over TCP.
   		It is also an one-way protocol, in the sense that only the client sends out RPP messages,
   		while the server only passively receives.</t>

   		<t>Each RPP server is in first place server in the protocol and listens
   		permanently on port 4343.
   		Meanwhile, it SHOULD act as well as client.
   		A RPP server acts as client when its delegated prefixes conduct as destination prefixes.
   		It pushes the inbound routing preferences
   		of its delegated prefixes to the RPP servers of source prefixes.
   		Routing preferences are coded in RPP messages.</t>

   		<t>Only one RPP message SHOULD be sent in each TCP connection.
   		TCP connection MUST be closed simultaneously once the message is received by the server side.</t>

   		<t>The selection of source prefixes to which routing preferences are sent to, 
   		is up to the AS managing the destination prefixes.
   		An example could be a subset of source prefixes that represent 95% of total incoming
   		traffic toward these destination prefixes.</t>

   	<section anchor="msg" title="RPP message format">
   		<t>
   		Each RPP message MUST begin with one single command to specify its type and functionality,
   		contain one single line,
   		and terminate with a CR/LF line terminator.
   		The command can be followed by lists of parameters.
   		The command and the parameter lists (if exist) MUST be separated by a single space.
   		Two neighbouring parameter lists MUST be separated by a tab symbol.
   		A list can contain multiple single-space-separated parameters.
   		<list style='empty'>
   			<t>MESSAGE: COMMAND LIST_1\tLIST_2\t...\tLIST_n\r\n</t>
   			<t>LIST: PARAM_1 PARAM_2 ... PARAM_n</t>
   		</list>
   		</t>
   	</section>

   	<section anchor="cmd" title="Command">
   		<t>Currently, only one command is defined: SETINPREF.
   		With this command, RPP server formulates inbound routing preference for its delegated
   		prefixes.
   		Three parameter lists SHOULD follow this command in order.
   		<list style='numbers'>
   			<t>TTL dictating the validity of the message, a list of one parameter in length.
   			TTL SHOULD be an integer ranging from 1 to 2147483647 (2^31-1), in seconds.</t>
   			<t>List of destination prefixes covered by this RPP message.
   			Prefixes in the list MUST be delegated by the RPP server.
   			They MUST be unique and non-overlapping.
   			Prefixes MUST be of same size as they are announced via inter-domain routing protocol.
   			They are REQUIRED to be written in <xref target="RFC4632">CIDR</xref> notation.</t>
   			<t>List of weighted upstream ASNs.
   			Upstreams are the last-one-hop ASes in the AS-PATHs via which traffic reaches the destination prefixes.
   			A weight SHOULD be attached to each ASN in the upstream list.
   			An upstream ASN and its weight SHOULD be concatenated with a colon.
   			Weight MUST be an integer ranging from 0 to 255.
   			Bigger value means higher preference.
   			When an upstream is neither preferred nor depressed, it SHOULD be attached with a weight equalling 127.
   			</t>
   		</list>
   		Assembling all the pieces, a SETINPREF type RPP message SHOULD fit in the following format:
   		<list style='empty'>
   			<t>SETINPREF TTL\tPf_1 Pf_2 ... Pf_n\tASN_1:W_1 ASN_2:W_2 ... ASN_m:W_m\r\n</t>
   		</list>
   		A source network is REQUIRED to fulfil the received preference as long as:
   		<list style='symbols'>
   			<t>TTL hasn't yet expired;</t>
   			<t>Source AS learns a route that passes through the preferred AS;</t>
   			<t>Forwarding the traffic through the preferred AS doesn't violate source AS's local policies.</t>
   		</list>
		A newly received RPP message SHOULD immediately replace the previous ones even if still valide.</t>

   		<t>An example of SETINPREF message is given below:
   		<list style='empty'>
   			<t>SETINPREF 3600\t185.86.52.0/24 185.86.53.0/24\t43142:10 199758:127 30851:200\r\n</t>
   		</list>
   		This message can only be sent by the RPP server delegating both prefix 185.86.52.0/24 and 185.86.53.0/24.
   		The routing preference contained in the message is valide for 1 hour.
   		Both destination prefixes prefer that traffic come in via AS30851.
   		AS199758 is as well acceptable but is less welcome than AS30851.
   		AS43142 SHOULD be avoided if possible.</t>

   	</section>
   	</section>


   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>TCP port 4343 need to be registered for RPP uses.</t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
     <t>It is RECOMMENDED that the RPP server of source prefix, i.e. server in RPP protocol,
     verifies that each received RPP SETINPREF message contains only destination prefixes
     that are delegated by the client, i.e. the RPP
     server sending the message.
     The validation can be done by performing RPP server discovery for each destination prefixe
     included in the message, and then verify whether their RPP server addresses are the same and are
     identical with the source IP address of the RPP message.</t>
     
     <t>If RPP communication is attacked or hijacked, only the transmission of
     correct inbound route preference is endangered, while no impact is expected for the control plane
     of underlying routing protocol. Hence, there is very limited security concerns related.</t>
   </section>
 </middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
   <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

   <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
    1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
    2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
       (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

    Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
    If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
    directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
    with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
    filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

   <references title="Normative References">
     <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
     &RFC2119;

     &RFC1035;

     &RFC4632;

   </references>
   <references title="Informative References">
     <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

     &RFC6830;

   <reference anchor="BGP_INBOUND_TE" target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1511.08336">
   	<front>
   		<title>On the use of BGP communities for fine-grained inbound traffic engineering</title>
   		<author initials="W.Q." surname="Shao">
   			<organization>Telecom ParisTech</organization>
   		</author>
   		<author initials="L." surname="Iannone">
   			<organization>Telecom ParisTech</organization>
   		</author>
   		<author initials="J.L." surname="Rougier">
   			<organization>Telecom ParisTech</organization>
   		</author>
   		<author initials="F." surname="Devienne">
   			<organization>BORDER 6</organization>
   		</author>
   		<date year="2015" />
   	</front>
   </reference>

   </references>

 </back>
</rfc>
